hello I'm your host David Barnard and my
guest today is Ferris saetti co-founder
and CEO of my swim Pro the leading swim
coaching app on the podcast I talked
with feris about how to build a Content
marketing flywheel the importance of
content that's inherently valuable and
why you shouldn't give up on content
marketing even if your early attempts
only get a few
views hey FIS thanks so much for joining
me on the podcast today David thanks for
having me excited to be here we got so
much to talk about I love your content
and how much success you've seen with
content marketing and so we're going to
get to that but to help the listeners
kind of understand the context around
that let's just start off with what is
my swim Pro yeah my swim Pro empowers
people to swim for life and we want to
be the One-Stop Shop app if someone
wants to improve their Fitness their
performance through swimming they come
to the app and it's like your personal
coach the difference between our app and
actually going to the pool and hiring a
coach is that you get a personalized
workout at a fraction of the cost of
actually hiring the coach so we started
this in 2015 and so far we've been
really focused on helping swimmers
improve their performance and health in
the water fantastic pitch number one
lesson if you're building an app you
need to have that good of a 60-second
pitch to explain your business to people
that was fantastic you can tell you've
done this a lot and do a lot of content
because that was very nailed down I know
you have several co-founders so tell me
just a little bit of the story of like
why you built the app and who your
co-founders are just a little bit of the
story of how you got to this point yeah
for sure and today our company is five
swimmers for swimmers and even in the
early days when we started the app it
was myself Adam oxner and Michael Alan I
actually met Adam who's our CTO now
through the swimming world so it was a
connection within swimming and we both
swam in University but it was really my
experience as a coach which really
pushed me to want to take this idea to
more than just an idea and actually
create an app because I was coaching
swimming and I was still swimming myself
but I had people asking me for workouts
for training for advice and what happens
when you get out of the system as I like
to call it where you're no longer on a
team you no longer have a coach there's
this huge gap and at the time and even
today really nothing was addressing this
Gap and the Gap is you want to swim but
you go to the pool and you have no idea
what to do so you could just go back and
forth and swim mindlessly which what a
lot of people do or you can follow a
structured training program which is
what you would do with a team as if you
had a coach so that didn't exist at the
time this was back 2014 2015 so the
first version of my swim Pro was simply
to give someone a workout as simple as
that you couldn't log it there's no
profile there's no analytics none of
this stuff the Apple watch didn't
actually exist yet and that's become a
major part of our business so when it
was just Adam Mike and I we were
basically hacking together different
ideas of how can we deliver this workout
in the most efficient and simple way and
obviously in the last seven eight years
it's become a lot more personalized a
lot more granular and Powerful as to
what it can actually do but from the
very beginning it was always how do we
help swimmers and we use the product
ourselves which I think is a really
important component of building a great
solution if you're solving your own
problem so did y'all raise money or did
you just bootstrap are you technical or
are your co-founders Technical and did
they kind of write the first app and you
were writing the programs and overseeing
yeah mix of everything so we're very
multi-skilled in the company even from
the founding days so I studied business
you know I don't have that technical
background I like to think I'm
selftaught in a of things but not at the
level of what we have today obviously so
Adam our CTO built the first version of
the iPhone app and the Apple watch
integration Michael did the Android app
but we skipped over an important fun
story when we started the app it
actually was before having an app at all
so we wanted to validate that this was
really a problem and with my technical
skills I basically bought a domain it
was my swim pal at the time my
swimel.com and I created a mockup of
what I thought the app would look like
and I had four value propositions on the
screen so I had the mockup of the app
and then an email capture and I used
Twitter to drive traffic to this website
the equivalent I think would be an
Instagram DM but you just kind of look
at the keyword swim and I just find
people who are tweeting about swimming
and I would just message them favor
their tweets send them to this URL and
then they put in their email to download
an app that didn't even exist yet still
a good way to validate demand and so
after just a couple of weeks I had 200
people who inputed their email to
download this app that didn't even exist
yet and a lot of these people had no
idea who they were so I was just finding
them on social media and I think the
social media landscape has changed but
this principle still technically applies
of here's the screen that we want to
test send traffic to it either paid or
free and then see what the demand
actually looks like so that was the end
of 2014 and then 2015 we had the myum
Pro app so that was the humble
beginnings it was bootstrapped we didn't
raise any money we weren't making any
money we can go into that we didn't
charge anything for the app at first the
first year we literally just were
listening to feedback from people who
use the app it wasn't that many and then
we just iterated on it over and over and
over 2016 we actually launched a
subscription offering for 10 bucks a
month you get basically more workouts we
actually paywalled some of the free
workouts that we did have in the app we
had different categories and then that's
when we did our first startup
accelerator so we raised $50,000 through
this accelerator we went through the
program and since then we've done a few
different rounds of equity crowdfunding
so we raised about $1.2 million mostly
through equity crowdfunding and it's
gotten us to where we are today but it's
been a wild ride even if I say that out
loud yeah how was the accelerator I've
had folks on who did why combinator
generally people have a good experience
there but I haven't talked to somebody
who's done a more traditional
accelerator like do you feel like that
experience was worth it do you think app
Founders should potentially go through
an accelerator or or do you think it
wasn't as helpful I think it's
definitely a caseby casee basis so for
me it was beneficial in our team because
even I had worked at other startups
before launching my swimpro so I had a
little bit of startup experience and
digital marketing but it wasn't like I
had started the company myself and the
rest of our co-founding team was the
same thing so if you're just getting
started even if you have business
experience it can be extremely
beneficial to learn the skills of
customer Discovery and to build a
network because you probably don't have
a network if you haven't started a
company or done something like that
before so I think in that perspective it
was very valuable what I do another
startup accelerator at this point
probably not if I were to start another
company but I think it really depends
Case by case I don't know I could
recommend it to like all app Founders
but if there's a program that is in line
with what you do like we did a program
it was through the University of
Michigan and so you don't have to have
gone to the university but I know a lot
of universities have a program like this
some are more geared towards health and
wellness they're partnered with a
healthare company so if your app is
aligned with the initiative of the
program that might make a lot of sense
yeah no that's super cool and then it
sounds like I was going to ask you what
the top two or three things were from
going through the accelerator it sounds
like networking and understanding some
of this product Market fit and being
able to connect with customers any other
top lessons that you feel like the
accelerator really helped with I think
refining the pitch you mentioned the way
I presented what we do but you're
presenting all the time and not only
when you meet with mentors they connect
you with mentors and you have to explain
what you do in a relatively quick
fashion the whole point of the
accelerator is at the end of the program
you do a three or five minute pitch to
The Community and it could be investors
or other folks and so if you don't have
a good pitch you will be forced to learn
how to pitch correctly and you get a lot
of feedback and you eliminate the things
that don't really matter and I think
doing those repetitions is really
valuable especially when you're still
trying to figure out what the heck
you're doing I think if you're a little
bit more mature in your business it's
probably not as useful because you've
already hopefully put in those reps but
yeah I think it was a good experience
overall all right so you went through
the accelerator you had collected these
emails you're kind of seeing early
traction what are some of the early
marketing things that you experimented
with and once you had that $50,000 in
the bank did you start experimenting
with paid or how did you get that early
momentum and then keep that momentum
going I think from day one it was a
Content marketing machine I can say that
now but at the time I didn't know what I
was doing we had a Blog we had social
media accounts started producing YouTube
videos literally every social media
channel I was on top of it and at the
time I just thought we have to be out
there people need to know that we exist
there's a name called my swimpro and it
has this blue icon the shirt that I'm
wearing but it's how do we get people
aware of this brand and then educate
people about the things that they need
to know to be successful in swimming so
in retrospect it all kind of makes sense
but to be honest in the moment I didn't
have as clear of a direction as I think
I do now and part of that is just my own
experience that was developed but also I
think the landscape has actually become
a lot more mature specifically the way
that you can leverage social media and
build a community digitally is a lot
more clear I think now there's a lot
more best practices compared to in 20145
it was still somewhat mature I guess but
it was relatively new compared to where
it is today so was creating a lot of
content Adam and Mike were building out
the app and then by 2018 is when we
actually hired our first additional team
member and it was Paige who's now our VP
of marketing so she's been with us for
like six years and basically I handed
off a lot of that content marketing to
her I continued to do a lot of it and
eventually became like the face of the
brand which was not intended either so
there's a whole bunch of things that
were lumped there when you were first
starting out with the content what kind
of stuff were you producing and were you
seeing traction with that content like
how did that go early on cuz even me
like I launched a big update to my
weather app recently we got some press
but once that dies down it's like you
got to get that ball rolling and I think
a lot of Founders expect I fell victim
to it as well they oh I'll get it out
there it's going to get some attention
and that's gonna snowball but actually
it takes a lot of deliberation I mean
some apps do just like explode out of
the gate but it sounds like y'all just
slow roll and built that flywheel that
just kept going but what did that really
look like in the early days sure in the
very beginning it was writing about an
article a week and I was just answering
basic swimming questions so if you
wanted to learn how to do a flip turn or
how to improve your freestyle technique
or your efficiency come and search
optimize things basically leveraging the
power of Google biggest search engine in
the world what are people searching on
the internet and I knew what people are
searching part because there are tools
that tell you this but also just
qualitatively because people are asking
us questions so for example the whole
reason why I started making YouTube
videos and it became sort of what it is
today is because we would get the same
questions via email every single day so
I would get you know in the app people
who are not as experienced in swimming
would ask a question and you know we
actually had my phone number in every
automated email that came from us I was
getting WhatsApp messages at all hours
of the day I was getting emails people
asking the same questions and one day I
was like you know what I'm just going to
make a video that explains this because
I've had to copy and paste like the
macro basically I'm telling the same
people over and over the same thing so I
got up a whiteboard and I just explained
swimming terminology and then I started
doing this on a weekly basis and it
became known as the Whiteboard Wednesday
so I stand in front of a whiteboard and
for 15 minutes I elaborate on something
swimming and in the very beginning like
I didn't even have any cool looking
footage it was just me standing in front
of a whiteboard which you think for
swimming like why would anyone pay
attention to that because I was
answering their questions so you go to
YouTube which is the second biggest
search engine in the world people have
questions and they want to learn and I
think now that's a little bit more
obvious than in 2015 but by 2018 like
after three years of consistently doing
this I became even more consistent and
then we started to see some compounding
traction but it didn't like all of a
sudden Spike the usage of the app I
think content Marketing in general is a
very long-term type of thing that you're
really building brand and you're
building trust so that way people not
only have the awareness that you exist
but they trust whatever it is that
you're telling them so that way if you
are to sell them something or come up
with an offer whether it's your app
subscription or something else then they
feel that they've already made a
connection with you and you know what
you're talking about and their
conversion to paying for whatever it is
that you're offering is going to be that
much higher so in 2015 to 2018 we're
talking thousands of social media posts
and hundreds of articles that I had
written so it's not like we wrote five
articles and then now we're SEO relevant
it was a very just consistently today
just a continuous routine and building
that pattern of habit and this is where
I think a lot of people get discouraged
with content marketing is I imagine in
those early days you'd put up a video
and you get tens of views or was it just
that slow building it it's a slow grind
so the very beginning like I mentioned I
just created the videos not to be a
YouTuber simply to answer the questions
people had so that might only be seven
people great now I don't have to write
seven emails I spent a few hours making
this video but I know that there's a
compounding effect of this is a better
delivery of the information anyway so in
the very beginning yeah I mean it was 75
views 300 views 4,000 now we have a few
of those videos of me that have millions
of views of me standing in front of a
whiteboard talking about swimming that
didn't happen overnight you know that
took years and at some level it is
discouraging I know I tell people that
and they're like how do you get half a
million followers on Instagram like
what's the trick well if you look at our
account we have like 7,000 posts it's
not like one blew up and then it
happened so I think there is some level
of patience that you have to have I
think for us and I remind our team like
if we don't have the patience to be
consistent and build the procedures and
the best practices then we shouldn't
really be doing it because if you're
trying to build a brand and trust that
takes a long time and I don't know who
said this quote but it's the concept of
brand is the only thing that transcends
technology so technologies will come and
go products will come and go the Apple
watch didn't exist when we started the
company the Apple watch is a majority
use case of our business in five 10
years like who knows what the thing is
the Apple Vision Pro like we don't know
what that is but if you have a brand and
you build trust and you have that
Community whatever the thing is if you
can innovate in it you'll have an
audience to purchase and engage with
whatever it is that you create what made
you stick with it because I think a lot
of people again starting content
marketing they put out a few blog posts
they do a few YouTube videos they get 75
views like you said and they're like
okay this is not working I'm going to
Pivot and try something else was there
early signs that it was was paying off
that made you stick with it or you just
had this Vision that you saw that it
would compound over time and just kept
at it like what kept you motivated
through those 75 view videos to keep
going I think there were a few things
one was simple naivity at the time I was
23 24 years old and I think I was really
deep in the hustle culture of like you
just need to work harder you don't have
the right to complain about anything so
I think that was part of it you're just
naive to like well I'm supposed to work
it's not really work smarter it's just I
was just working hard like that's part
of it the other is you have to love what
you do so like I'm the one who's the
face behind the camera and a lot of this
stuff and I love it so it doesn't really
feel like a lot of work to me even
though it might take a certain amount of
time the mental load I think is what
actually inhibits a lot of people
because the thought of like okay I need
to prepare what I'm gonna write in the
article or if I'm G to make a video I
need to have all my talking points and
even from the very beginning I was
pretty fast at doing a lot of these
things because I'm talking about
something that I know I think if
someone's trying to be the online expert
and create the content or build that
flywheel if they're not interested in
the topic if they don't have the
expertise it's gonna feel like a huge
mental weight how do you find the time
to do this it really doesn't take as
much time as you think it just is
decision fatigue and that decision
fatigue can be very overwhelming so I
think there's a few variables between my
naivity and as well as just I love doing
it and then having some level of vision
that you know I'm not here to pack up
tomorrow I'm here to build a brand and I
think I got a little bit of a taste of
success somewhat early on in the sense
that hey wait a second you know I
created this video how to do a flip turn
as an example it did take off and it got
75,000 views okay well why did that work
because it clearly answered a need in
the market and I think it goes back to
more specifically our app the success
that taste of success it doesn't need to
be 75,000 views all it takes is a few
people to say this video answered my
question the most common one that we
have which is the impetus for this is
four time 50 I am so if you see that in
our app or you see it in swing that
means you do a 50 of each stroke in the
individual medly order so if you just
see it on paper and you don't know
anything about swimming what does this
mean so just answering that question in
a video and being able to send that to
people and getting the oh this helped a
lot thank you like as simple as that
that is very gratifying to know oh okay
this actually delivered value and now
they use the app and tying it back to
the subscription they're probably going
to keep paying for it because they
understand how it works what were the
signs that it was starting to pay off
and how did you measure the impact I
mean were you tracking views compared to
app downloads and subscribers like did
you have a spreadsheet that one video
you said that did kind of go somewhat
viral I guess 75,000 views is a lot for
a video you it's not Millions like
Marquez brownley or whatever but that's
pretty good were you tracking that
impact like we got 75,000 views and that
led to X number of downloads and X
number of downloads led to Y number of
subscribers I will say we're a lot
better at this now than at the time at
the time it was more about I need to
make content let me go write some
articles and I had a weekly Cadence of
just building stuff and then when Paige
joined we basically built a mini Army to
compound that but in terms of tracking
we were tracking everything but it's
hard to measure the direct impact we
have really good metrics around each
individual social Channel now we use the
app store like custom product URLs and
we actually measure how many leads we
get from YouTube vers we have a
different URL for Instagram stagram for
YouTube for Facebook for our website and
then we can see and attribute Revenue
directly to that that's a very recent
thing that we actually I sound like know
what I'm talking about but that's only
in the last few months we literally
implemented that but in the very
beginning it was more just I was willing
to take the short-term potential loss in
time for the long-term benefit of
building a brand and now I think it's
easier to quantify because we have two
full-time video editors on our team and
most apps don't have something like that
and I can better justify the expense of
that and the way our team is set up
because we able to monetize beyond our
app subscription through YouTube AdSense
through brand Partnerships and there's a
whole story of how we thought about
building that but now it's easier to Roi
that because I know how much money that
alone is making so even if the app was
not benefiting at all it's still Roi
positive just for this segment of the
business now I want to be able to more
accurately attribute and the product
URLs are one step in that direction but
it is difficult like I'm not gonna sit
here and say we have the golden bullet
of how Instagram view converts to XYZ
value in our app I do think there would
be some level of shrinkage if we just
all of a sudden disappeared off the
internet so if none of the content
exists if our brand disappeared we would
certainly see some level of hit in
organic traffic through the App Store
and how people are discovering us we
don't do this but some apps they
actually ask you how you came across the
app in the first place directly in the
onboarding we've done that through our
surveys so we qualitatively measure to
our subscribers and even free users how
you learned about the app and we can see
some numbers there so there is some
level of measurement but I don't have
the perfect answer you know it sounds
like you really started on YouTube and
that's kind of been a main stay I hadn't
heard anybody say that but actually
makes a ton of sense that YouTube is the
second largest search engine in the
world that people are looking for
answers to their questions and they'll
go to Google but then I mean I do this I
go to YouTube you know I need to do
something with my washer dryer it's like
what what do I do I go to YouTube and
figure it out so it makes a lot of sense
but how did the channels evolve over
time like did you initially start with
YouTube and then slowly move to
Instagram and others or did you just
glass to all those social media channels
and what does that mix look like today
well actually we started with Twitter I
don't remember if it was my personal
Twitter or the my swim Pro Twitter at
the time to DM people and get on to that
landing page but it was actually Twitter
because it seemed the easiest to get
started like tweeting about swimming or
Twitter's more events driven for anyway
so when there was a swimming competition
happening it was very easy to jump on
that but very shortly after I basically
created an account for every channel and
some have come and gone over the years
so for example Snapchat was something
that I was more engaged with and now we
don't do anything with Snapchat Tik Tok
is a relatively new one so we didn't
start doing Tik Tok until 2019 which now
it sounds like we've been doing it for a
while but relative to the other channels
it was a latecomer in that regard I
think the YouTube Focus has really come
to where it is now only in the last few
years so I did mention we have all the
channels a few reasons why I choose to
focus on YouTube and why I want our
company focus on YouTube is because it
is the best place for the deeper
connection so you can have a big Twitter
following for example and now it's a
little different because you can have
longer threads and conversations like
that but it's a lot different when
you're hearing and seeing the person
explain something to you so when it goes
back to building trust there's a reason
why YouTubers can charge the highest for
any kind of a brand deal because they
have the trust of the person that
they're communicating with and so even
if it's not fully aligned like right now
it's I'm not saying you know I have all
these subscribers and our company page
has all these subscribers we don't have
that many app subscribers right so
there's a lot of people who are engaging
with the content that are maybe not
interested in the app because the app
has a very specific use case has a very
targeted Persona that we're designing
the product experience around whereas
YouTube it's oh you want to go swimming
like anyone who wants to improve
swimming in any capacity competitive
young old beginner Advanced it it really
doesn't matter and we have content that
can apply to them so maybe that opens
the doors for new features in our app
down the road new apps new products new
Services there's a lot of different
things that we could expand to but I
think there's a lot of moving parts so
it's hard to pick one social Channel and
that's what you should start with I
think it depends on what kind of a brand
you're looking to build and how it fits
into your overall marketing acquisition
funnel has Tik Tok been a good channel
for yall have you seen a lot of traction
have you had some videos go viral on Tik
Tok or is it just kind of you're there
it's easy to take the content you're
already producing for YouTube chop it up
and throw it on there uh yeah I mean
it's interesting what works on some
channels doesn't really work on other
channels so we can take content on
YouTube and chop it up in a few
different ways some of that will perform
on Tik Tok but it won't perform on
Instagram reals so in terms of to answer
your question like is Tik Tok working I
think we have like 300 something
thousand followers but I wouldn't say
it's a primary channel of acquisition
and awareness for us we have had some
posts that have millions or tens of
millions of views but it's not okay we
got 10 million views on this video and
now that gave us 50,000 new downloads
it's like that one million view video
may have had nothing to do with our app
which could be seen as a problem as like
well now you have a bunch of bad traffic
I don't really see it that way there are
some people who probably did find Value
and now they went to other content and
now they ended up downloading the app
but it goes back to building the brand
in this world we are fighting for
attention so whether it's in the app or
someone's phone right I don't know what
the hours are but people are spending
five hours a day in their phone where
are they spending those five hours
they're not spending it in your app
unless your app is Instagram or Tik Tok
or YouTube right so because people are
spending their time in those apps you
want to make sure that you have a
presence so for us it's being everywhere
all the time no matter what it's a lot
more work and you need more manpower to
be able to do that but depends on what
level you're trying to compete at in
that attention game you kind of alluded
to this but now that you do have such a
big YouTube following specifically you
kind of mentioned that the content
itself is monetized I thought that was
really interesting that most people
would view the content as solely content
marketing but tell me about how the
content is actually driving revenue and
is a second pillar of Revenue to the app
yeah that's a great point because when
you get to a certain level of viewership
especially on long form content you can
monetize in few different ways so
YouTube does pay the Creator directly
and you know everyone's seeing the ads
at the beginning or in the middle of a
video if it's if it's a longer video you
might have several ads you can go online
very easily and see what the cpms are
but for every thousand views of a video
you could get anywhere from three to $15
depending on your category so if you
have a video with a million views that
could make $110,000 so if you look at
one of your favorite YouTubers and you
see every video they're and let's say
they're doing tech reviews like MKBHD
and every video he makes has five
million views and his CPM in that
category is probably $10 to $20 so each
of those videos you do the math on that
he's making maybe $50,000 a video that
pays for his production team now for him
he's a pure YouTuber so that's his
primary thing if you're building an app
like us I have my channel the company's
Channel we monetize through YouTube
AdSense which is like a nice to have but
also now we can do brand Partnerships so
these are the shout outs in the middle
of the video that you've seen on YouTube
where the Creator is promoting some
product that might be relevant that're
actually using in the video or elsewhere
and so those will actually pay even more
money than the CPM rate because the
brand knows that you're communicating
with a very dedicated audience so it
goes back to that trust Factor so the
more trust you have the more dedicated
your viewership now you can add another
layer of monetization which is the brand
deals we're starting to talk more about
like the content creator World more than
the app world but I feel like I've
stepped into this role now I didn't
really plan on it but since we're there
and there's an opportunity to not only
Market swimming and then get more
audience to the brand but then also
monetize it this is really the only
method of marketing that I know where
you can actually do marketing to get
more customers and you get paid to get
more customers to do the marketing yeah
so it's kind of interesting but I think
this goes back to the fact that you're
creating content that is super valuable
for people and I think that's where
people who think I'm going to do content
marketing their content often is overly
focused on the app like I watch it few
of your YouTube videos a few of them I
watch you don't even mention my swim Pro
so it's not like the video is an ad for
the app directly you're just creating
really good content and so it kind of
makes sense that by creating that really
great content you're creating multiple
flywheels that you're building this
audience that is monetizable through the
content itself which I do think that's
really cool and like maybe not as
directly relevant to this audience in
that a lot of folks have not built up
that kind of Content Library that's
eventually monetizable but I think it's
cool that you built it and it's
something others can aspire to do is
that if you build this up where you are
creating great content it's not just
going to drive downloads and subscribers
you can eventually potentially monetize
that content directly so I do think
that's relevant and super interesting so
I did want to dive back into the content
production itself I think this is where
you started out just you and a
whiteboard but how did it evolve from
there and like what is that content
production look like today and then how
did it evolve over time yeah this is a a
very interesting story on I think just
scalability in general it's applicable
to more than just content marketing so
in the very beginning let's take the
Whiteboard Wednesday which is the weekly
video series that had a Blog and an
email Associated to it so basically it
would be Wednesday in the morning we' go
to a wiiw work and I would think what
video am I going to make today so
literally it would just be like my
Wednesday project and I would think okay
what's the video I would draft it up
film it
edit it and ship it all in the same day
try and keep it as simple as possible
write the email write the blog based on
what I said in the video and that was
what I did for basically a couple of
years and then eventually it became a
little bit more sophisticated when we
had another team member where I
basically handed off a few of those
responsibilities so I would still make
the video and even edit the video but
then I wouldn't do the blog I wouldn't
do the email eventually we hired a video
editor to take the editing off my plate
so all I had to do was come up with the
concept and then just go and film the
video and then upload it and then I
would do a review next thing you know
it's on the internet along the way we
would take that one long form piece of
content and we would split it up into
multiple versions so we would have the
shorter form content posts for different
social media channels and what you
mentioned a few minutes ago about not
having an overly salesy feel to the
content because fundamentally I'm not
trying to sell someone our app I'm
trying to help them improve their
swimming so if they came to YouTube to
search for a specific skill like how to
do a flip turn they want to learn how to
do a flip turn our app doesn't teach you
how to do a flip turn what it does do is
it teaches you how to structure your
workout so you get the most out of your
time so when it is applicable inside the
long form and inside the Articles the
emails and everything it makes a lot of
sense to answer their question of how to
do a flip turn and then also share and
if you really want to take your s to the
next level this is how you can do it
with the my Pro app and yes you can do
your flip turns inside the my Pro app
just as an example so we did that for a
few years and then if you fast forward
to where we are today it's a little bit
more team intensive production in the
sense that now we're on location when I
film some of these things we might not
do it at a whiteboard I might be
standing at a swimming pool we might be
hosting an inperson event like a swim
camp our videographer is with me we're
at the pool deck he's filming me and
then two weeks later it's on YouTube
there's a few steps I skipped in there
but it's probably not as applicable for
this audience because we now we have
like an in-house studio so we have two
full-time video editors our VP of
marketing manages that team I have
someone who just manages my brand deals
that come through myself and the company
and he's part-time works on commission
and then we have another team member who
just does the social media posting a
team of five people is the engine that I
was basically doing you know a fraction
of that by myself so now it's more team
more expense but we're also making more
money through the AdSense the brand
deals and the app is in a stronger
position so it all works to complement
each other that's really cool when did
you post your first YouTube video on
this channel on the stuff that we're
talking about 2015 I've been making
videos my whole life so I have another
Channel I call it my uncut Channel like
15 years ago wow okay so eight years of
building to get to the point where
hiring five full-time people makes sense
to do the content Productions so again I
think people get discouraged with
content marketing or even think if I'm
going to do content marketing right I
need five people today and they go out
and hire all these people and they get
75 views and it doesn't work it's like
you got to build this up over time and I
think you build building this channel is
the perfect example of that that just
continuing to grind away at it and
creating that value can snowball into
where those five people full-time does
make sense yeah if anything it's
actually much easier now I know people
say there's so much competition how do
you stand out but the barrier to entry
is like nothing so if someone is
watching or listening to this video or
this podcast you have a smartphone
probably with fast internet that shoots
in 4k you can get on Amazon or
microphone so you have Crystal Clear
audio in 4k you can record in slow
motion you get cap cut you have videos
that go viral like easily if anything
it's easier now and you don't need five
people to scale up really quick whereas
eight years ago yes there were
smartphones but you actually needed a
decent camera otherwise it would look
pretty crummy you needed a very
expensive microphone now microphone's 20
bucks and you got something not amazing
but you have something to kick you off
so I think the barrier is definitely
lower which means there's more
competition but if you're adding genuine
value and that's part of your long-term
vision of brand if it correlates to your
app or whatnot then yeah I think you
should go for it you just got to be
ready to keep doing it for a long time
you kind of touched on this a little bit
but I wanted to go a little deeper on
how you think about when to add a CTA to
the app and when to not so how do you
think about that there's actually
different schools of thought on this I
think I'm somewhere in the middle so on
the one side you have people like Gary
ve and he's all about jab jab right hook
so you give away 10,000 pieces of
content you build the ultimate brand
trust and then in one of them you
transact so it's very very extreme you
also have people like he's a big
YouTuber Ali abdal and it's like I think
a 99 to one rule so you give 99% of the
time and only 1% of your audience you
actually even expect to transact with
you but the other 99 percentile they're
not going to transact and the idea is
you build an audience so massive and
you're so dominant in your category that
1% is actually huge but if you sell sell
sell well now your audience is going to
be a fraction of the size and yeah you
might get 50% penetration but you got
50% penetration of seven people so it's
trying to find that balance I think I'm
somewhere in the middle in terms of how
you think about adding the CTA this is
tricky but you always want to come back
to what is the point of that specific
piece of content are you truly trying to
sell something or are you trying to
answer the question of the audience or
the viewer or the subscriber the app
user whoever it is so if the piece of
content going back to my flip turn
analogy if the whole point of the video
and why they came to it in the first
place is to learn how to do that
specific thing you have to really focus
on answering that question because if
you do they're going to continue to want
to see stuff that you create and that's
how you build a trust and you could have
the call to action in that piece of
content but it might actually make sense
to have it in a different piece of
content that maybe you know that first
piece is your lead generation you get
them to follow you and pay attention to
what you do and then it makes more sense
to actually transact I think the best
approach is more integrated I'll give
you an example of what we're doing right
now so I'm currently in Dubai and I'm
training for the Masters World
Championships in Doha so in this series
I'm doing a five-part video where I'm
showing how I prepare for the world
championships and I'm using the my
swimpro app to train for this
competition so every single video I have
the app on screen showing the workouts
that I'm actually doing and so I'm not
selling the app I'm just using the app
as my tool to achieve the results that
I'm trying to show so if someone's been
following along this journey it's cool
they feel like they're making a
connection they're watching like this
guy trained for a big competition but
the way I'm doing it is the ultimate
Showcase of what the app can do and I'm
showing the true power of it and I'm
never really selling the app but the app
is on the screen for 30% of the time so
I think that's like the perfect method
of integration and I think when we have
done that and we've created stories
where like I did a challenge where I
swim every day for 30 days straight I
swam a mile for 100 days in a row and so
we made videos for each of these things
I'm not selling the app per se I might
have some sentences of like how you see
how I'm doing it in the app and you can
follow along or whatever but it's more
about how can I integrate the experience
of what I'm teaching what I'm educating
or the story that people are following
along and also showcase yes I'm using
the app to be able to do this and then
just one more thing that's just on like
how my perspective is as a company we do
have our own YouTube channel as a
company and that we're using to tell
stories gold medal moments we call them
people who have had success they lost
100 pounds they did a crazy amount of
swimming at the age of 67 and how do
they do their crazy swimming they use
the my swim Pro and so it's a very clean
way to integrate without just being an
advertisement you mentioned that kind of
99 to1 where would you say you end up
landing on like how many videos do have
call to actions versus ones that don't I
think at some level I do want every
video to have at least a minor call to
action some might be a sentence that
integrates with the storyline pretty
well and it could just be something
quick on screen I think the meat of it
is maybe 30% of the videos have a very
very solid insertion meaning over 60
seconds where it's a very clear like I'm
teaching you this thing and the way that
I'm teaching you is showing you how it's
done in the myum Pro app where the app
screen is on the video screen for an
extended period of time so maybe a third
of videos have that level then you might
say well okay so 70% of the videos don't
have an advertisement in them and it is
a more subtle approach to it I think as
a viewer you have to think about it too
like from your own perspective if you're
following someone on any social media
you don't want to see them just selling
you something all the time you are
either following them because one of
three things if someone's listening or
watching and they take away anything
from this content marketing you have to
do one of three things you either have
to educate people you have to entertain
them or you inspire them and so if you
think about anyone you follow on social
media any plat they're either teaching
you something they're entertaining you
in some way or you feel inspired now if
you're really good at any of those
that's great but if you're amazing you
can do multiple at the same time and I'm
sure people are thinking about
individuals they follow on social or
brands that are able to connect the
entertaining part and the inspiration or
the inspiration with the education I
think for us it's a combination of those
some videos might be more inspirational
when you hear about a 67-year-old who
did some amazing feet and
that's inspirational it maybe wasn't the
most entertaining thing but maybe you
were educated as well I think my style
is less inspirational it's more
educational with a little bit of
entertainment I don't want to Spill the
Beans I have a very entertaining I'm
doing I'm swimming a mile with a certain
piece of clothing on multiple pieces of
clothing right so that's going to be
more entertainment but a lot of the
content is more educational where I'm
teaching you something I did want to
move on from content marketing and talk
about a few other aspects of the
business again not every app is going to
succeed with content marketing I think a
lot more could than have maybe tried or
have dabbled in it and then not found
success and kind of given up but I
wanted to talk about a few other things
what other forms of marketing have you
experimented with and or found success
or is content marketing really where
it's at for my swim per content is the
bulk of it but we have tried paid
acquisition I think we've done three
different rounds of paid acquisition at
different points of the company life
cycle we're sort of in the middle of the
third one right now and a lot of it like
what's the difference between the three
it's who we worked with you know we were
doing sometimes inhouse working with
agencies the product was in a different
spot when it comes to the download
conversion rate the price point is
different so now I'd like to say we're
in our third attempt at trying to make
it work at scale this is probably our
best attempt and we have the best
analytics infrastructure in place to
actually assess the effectiveness of the
campaigns that we're running on various
channels so I'd like to think that we're
moving in the right direction but paid
acquisition is very tough and I think
depending on the funding of the business
so for us we don't have a bank account
with $17 million in it so when you're
doing ads you have to be more methodical
your test budget is not as large and the
algorithms especially these days they
favor big budgets and they will put a
better audience to a bigger budget as
horrible as that sounds I mean that's
the reality of it so yeah you can make
it work with a small budget great I'd
say we're still trying to figure that
out that's one Avenue of acquisition
that we've experimented with over and
over we talked about content marketing
quite a bit another Avenue of
acquisition that we're looking at is
inperson events we've gone to events we
host swim camps now that's one method
but that's not the most scalable because
you can only have so many people at an
in-person event we have some other
creative ideas that we haven't yet
executed on like how can we put put
ourselves at every swimming pool in
America or every pool in the world right
there's in the US there's 300,000
commercial pools there's 10 million or
so like private pools so how do we just
get some kind of a presence at a swing
pool so we haven't figured that out yet
maybe it's through different
Partnerships that's one Avenue of
acquisition that we're pursuing right
now but It's Tricky especially when you
get to a certain scale where you
basically tap out your organic traffic
which is kind of where we are right now
there's only so many more organic
downloads that we can get that's not
going to 5x our growth so what can we do
that's not depending on someone going to
the App Store and typing in swim that
can get us another one that we're even
testing right now is referral marketing
so in app being able to invite someone
getting different promotions and
incentivizing why the power user would
want to invite someone in the first
place these are some different things
that we're testing no Silver Bullet yet
but we'll keep trying so you mentioned
you're in phase three I think a lot of
folks can learn from failure as much as
success what would you say were the
failures of phase one and two like what
did you experiment with what were the
results you saw that you had to give up
on it the biggest mistake you can make
is not having the right analytics in
place so if you don't know okay you
spend $1,500 what happened like if you
don't know what actually ends up
happening with that 1500 and you don't
have some level of confidence in the
attribution that's the biggest mistake
so you really can't put any significant
budget besid just oh we'll boost this
post and see if we get more app
downloads right that's not how you scale
something so I think that was one
mistake that we did we didn't have the
right infrastructure in place another
thing is just making sure you work with
the right people and also making sure
that you on top of the analytics so now
that you have the analytics in place
okay that's good that's one step but now
are you actually like paying attention
to the analytics and making improvements
and iterations fast enough so that way
you can improve and not burn too much
money in the process because the reality
is like any AB test you know a lot of
them are going to fail so you have these
ads these different creatives you don't
know which one is going to hit and so if
it takes you a long time to figure out
which ones are your winners and which
ones are your poor performing ad ads
then you're just going to end up
spending more and more money and you're
eventually going to have to stop because
you're not able to get results quick
enough to justify the amount of money
that you're burning so that's another
and yeah there's probably quite a bit of
smaller little learnings but yeah those
are the big ones as we're wrapping up I
did want to ask you about one more thing
I know you've done a lot of price
testing I actually saw several reviews
complaining about the price no matter
what you priced you're going to get
complaints like I priced my weather app
at $40 a year and I got three or four VI
saying oh that's just way too much money
and so you were charging and have been
experimenting with $180 a year now
totally different you're replacing a
swim coach just the weather app there's
way more competition so I probably have
more reason to reassess my pricing but
what led you to that
$180 price point and then how's that
been working for you from the beginning
of the app we have had probably eight
different price points at some level of
duration meaning over three months or
six months when we first launched the
app it was free then we added a $10 a
month option because like I said in the
beginning naivity like that felt right
10 bucks a month that's what other apps
are I think at the time most fitness
apps were like 79.99 a year and they had
an offering that was 15 20 bucks a month
10 bucks a month so 10 bucks a month
sounded right and then we added a yearly
offering around 100 bucks then it was
120 then it was 180 and what what
happened is we didn't really see much of
a change in conversion rate so we kept
on increasing the price and we kept on
making the app better and better and
here's the key so we've done AB testing
we continue to do ab testing the thing
is inside of your segments of people who
are paying for the app there are some
segments that are willing to spend way
more than others and I think this is a
mistake that we've done recently where
we kind of just bundle everyone together
well we do the ab test and this is the
price that wins yes that's the price
that wins for the overall population but
there's a segment maybe 20% of your
paying customers that could pay 10 times
what your current offering is but you're
not charging anything else so the only
way to do that is having different
pricing packages and different product
offerings and any mature business has
these there's a reason why there's more
than one iPhone there's a reason why
there's multiple in a car the same car
could be $40,000 or $90,000 so there's a
reason why there's different levels to
that so I think for us one thing we're
looking at doing is how do we continue
to test not only the price point but the
way that we're actually packaging the
offer to serve different segments of the
audience that have different problem
sets but also and maybe more importantly
different willingness to pay and price
sensitivity actually one of the guys
that was on this podcast the founder and
CEO of the ladder app he actually
mentioned there was a a price test
sensitivity thing that you can do I
actually after listening to his podcast
on this show I actually went and we did
a survey implementing that exact study
where you ask four questions to see what
people think is too expensive so this is
a qualitative way to assess and you end
up with like four lines on a graph then
between the two lines is your ideal
price point so we sent this out for free
members we sent it out for paid members
and it's remarkable to see just how many
people are willing and able to spend way
more money than we're currently charging
so that the actual average ends up being
around what our price point is now 20 a
month or 120 or 100 a year but there are
people who are willing to spend $200
$300 per year we don't have a product
offering right now and a packaging that
is able to access that kind of a price
sensitivity so I think we're still
evolving and as the business becomes
more mature and I think like any more
mature business that's been around for a
while you have to be able to create
different offerings and packaging to
different segments of the market with
different price sensitivity for those
who do experiment with higher prices and
get those kind of reviews do you have
any advice like do you just ignore those
personally when I get those reviews at
like oh $40 is way too much I'm like
dude like come on that's not that much
money and we're doing something really
unique like are you able to just ignore
that or how do you put that in
perspective I think part of it has to go
with the packaging so one mistake that
we've done is it's not really a mistake
but as we've transition we went from a
completely free app to a paying app and
we we've actually over the years we've
taken away free features we put them
behind a pay wall so some of the
complaints are attributed to that so at
some level yeah rightfully so they could
do something for free now they can't so
you build a level of entitlement with
your community because they feel
entitled to use the software that you've
created for free because that's how
they've has done it so now if you all of
a sudden charge for the thing that you
spend time and resources on and now they
have a hissy fit so I think it's just
how you package it that's one area we
can definitely improve in because if
people know that this is a paid offering
but no one has the right to complain
because they don't feel entitled to
something for free but if you advertise
yeah this is the best app for free and
you can do all these things and then
they get into the app and they can't do
a lot of the things yes they can do some
things but like the good stuff is behind
a payall then you're going to have some
level of resentment that you create and
I think every company at some level has
had to deal with this what I've noticed
though is that the more premium you're
offering at at a higher price point and
the more you package it in that
orientation you just attract a clientele
that are just ready to pay anyway
because some people will complain at any
price point even if it was 45 cents
they're still going to complain whereas
other people they won't want to buy a
product that is perceived a lower value
so there's a little bit of psychology
that plays into this and I think it's
trying to balance the qualitative
psychology with the data this is
something we're constantly trying to
balance is being data driven at the same
time looking at how humans behave which
is not in line with what a logical
decision would actually be I think we've
seen this kind of industrywide I like
that you brought up the word entitlement
because I think this is something any
subscription app practitioner should be
aware of and be thinking about in how
they do like you said the pricing and
packaging how they balance premium and
all that kind of stuff is that folks are
used to getting things for free and
paying with attention with their data
and so there is this entitlement nature
I think to software is like that people
just kind of expect software to be free
but I think what we've started to see
over the last five to even 10 years is
just this slow kind of shift of the
industry of hey software can actually
create a ton of value in your life and
that value is worth paying for that's
what actually makes me really bullish
for the next 10 years is that more and
more consumers are starting to actually
not feel entitled to software but
actually see it as something valuable
that they are going to be willing to pay
for so like that person today who would
complain about just 45 cents maybe in
three or four or five more years I think
the market for people who are actually
willing to pay for software that
delivers value to them will continue
expanding over time and so it's like we
have this dual flywheel going on in the
industry of creating more and better
software and then attracting more users
to that software and then more and more
of those users being willing to pay over
time and so if you are getting those
complaints like f is and myself about
people saying uh it's too much money and
why should I have to pay and all this
kind of stuff I think we can all take a
little bit of heart in the fact that
that's going to continue to get better
and better over time I mean have you
seen that I mean you've been doing it
eight years now people willing to pay
more and then now as you're charging
even more people being I mean it's crazy
to me in some ways that people will say
on a survey that they're willing to
spend hundreds of dollars but it also
does speak to your category that a swim
coach would be way more expensive than
hundreds of dollars a year and you're
delivering a level of value maybe not
quite like having a personal coach but
directionally you're creating a ton of
value that would otherwise cost way more
money how have you seen that kind of
value perception evolve over the eight
years you've been doing this yeah I
think one guy that you had on Eric
Crowley he he was great showing all the
industry data where he was showing how
the wind is in our sales the market is
moving in the direction that more and
more people are willing and able to
spend money on app subscriptions that's
growing faster than the population it's
growing faster than inflation it's
growing faster than adjusted gross
income so I have seen this in the last
eight years so in 2015 very few apps had
a subscription business bus model at the
scale that most apps do today and even
in our category of health and fitness
the big apps of the day were my fitness
pal Under Armour acquired them and also
M my fitness M my run all those apps
were completely free they never had any
paid offering the only way they could
monetize was they had 20 million people
using the thing so they had sponsors
inside of the app and they were
basically that attention value that's
how they were able to monetize only
recently in the last five years has it
become the norm for every health and
fitness app to have some level of inapp
purchase subscription and I think the
perception is now that people are
willing and able to pay at a much higher
level because the consumer Behavior has
shifted where it is now an expectation
at a certain cohort where people will
actually spend the money because now
it's a line item in their budget because
they've already spent money somewhere
else for an app and so I think what
we're doing in swimming what you're
doing bringing on all these apps and
talking about this it is pushing the
market more and more in the direction
because most people who use the myON Pro
app and pay for the subscription we are
not their only subscription they're
probably paying for some other
subscription whether it's Trava or
literally any other app they could be
using and we're not the only
subscription so I think that benefits
everyone there is a little bit of
subscription fatigue that I know people
have talked about that where it's like I
don't want to have 17 different
subscriptions that goes back to
competition so what kind of value Are
you delivering in your category and is
it better than what someone else can
deliver in the category and I think as a
capitalistic system I think that's good
I think it's healthy and it pushes us to
deliver the best value no matter what
well as we wrap up anything else you
wanted to share are you hiring I'm going
to put links to the app and your YouTube
channel so people can see what kind of
content you're producing see what's
going on in all those different channels
but anything else you wanted to share as
we wrap up I think that was great I hope
people enjoyed this conversation yeah if
anyone wants to get into swimming we are
the app for you so connect online on
LinkedIn and wherever else and hope to
see you guys in the pool all right
thanks so much for joining me thanks
David thanks so much for listening if
you have a minute please leave a review
in your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. subclub do.com to
join our private
[Music]
community